# José Jair Santanna

Ph.D. Researcher, Lecturer, Network Security Specialist & (Big) Data Analyst

#### Contact

Drienerlolaan 5, Zilverling 5110, 7522 NB Enschede, The Netherlands.

+31 (6) 42330703

#### http://jairsantanna.com j.i.santanna@utwente.nl

## Languages

portuguese native english fluency spanish comprehension dutch comprehension

## **Programming**

Bash, Python, C#,SQL PIG, Spark & Impala

## **Professional Objective**

A research & development position with focus on network security and the use of big data technologies to improve network data analysis. A position where I can transfer my enthusiasm, knowledge, skills and experience into meaningful innovation that improve the security in computer networks, specially in the Internet.

## **Education**

2013-Now	Doctor	University of Twente, The Netherlands
	"The DDoS as a \$ervice Phenomenon"	
2010–2012	Master in Computer Science "A BPM-based Solution for Inter-domain of this work generated a product still in and Research Network (RNP) (Link: http://dx.	use by the Brazilian National Education
2005–2010	<b>Bachelor</b> in Computer Engineer "A Comparative Evaluation of DCCP Pro	Federal University of Pará, Brazil tocol in a Experimental Mesh Network."

## **Experience**

#### **Technical Adviser**

2016	To the Dutch National Cyber Security Center and the Scientific Research & Documen-	
	tation Center The Netherlands	
	For the production of a report on "Cyber metrics 2016: DDoS and Malware" requested by the <i>Dutch Ministry of Security and Justice</i> .	
2016	<b>To the Yokohama National University</b> For the production of a report on "Reflection & Amplification DDoS attacks" requested by the <i>Japanese Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications</i> .	

#### **Assistant Professor**

2012–2013 **University of Santa Cruz do Sul (UNISC)**Tasks & Responsibilities: Supervise students and teach the following courses: Computer Networks, Computer Network Management, and Digital Systems.

#### **Guest Lecturer**

2015 & 2016	Product Design to Online Business (course)	University of Twente, The Netherlands
	Audience: bachelor students of industrial engin	eering and business information
	technology.	
2015	Network Security (course)	University of Twente, The Netherlands
	Audience: master and bachelor students of c	computer science, electrical en-
	gineer, and telematics from the University of T	wente, 3TU cyber security, and
	members of ICT labs.	
2015	Cybercrime & Cybersecurity (minor)	University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students from University of Twente, European Research Center for Information (ERCIS), Westfälische Wilhelms - Univerität Münster, Universität Innsbruck, and University of Leicester.

## **Software Developer**

2015–Now **Distributed Denial of Service Attacks Database (DDoSDB)** 

Link: http://bit.ly/ddos\_db

An initiative to develop the largest open database with DDoS attacks.

Languages: Python, Bash, Pig Latin & Apache Impala

2010–2011 Management Environment of Inter-domain Circuits for Advanced Networks (MEICAN)

Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/

Development of an Executable Network Management Policies Editor sponsored

by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP)

Language: WS-BPEL

2009 Support for Planning Sustainable Electrical Power Generation via Vegetable Oil.

Desktop application sponsored by Eletronorte, subsidiary of the major Brazilian

power utility (Eletrobrás). Language: C#.Net & mySQL

## **Student Supervisor**

[M.Sc. Degree] Joey de Vries [Cum Laude], Justyna Chromik [Cum Laude], Wouter de Vries, Mark Wierbosch, and Jarmo van Lenthe.

[B.Sc. Degree] Roeland Krak, Max Kerkers, Dirk Maan, Jochum Börger, and Guilherme Dressler.

#### **International Conference Reviewer**

IFIP Networking (2014–2016), IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium (2014 & 2016), Asia-Pacific Network Operations and Management Symposium (2013 & 2014), IFIP/IEEE Integrated Management (2015), International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (2015), International Conference on Network and Service Management (2013–2015), EUNICE Conference (2013) & IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communications(2011)

## **Awards**

2015	Best Ph.D. 'Elevator Pitch' (1	1 <sup>st</sup> Place)	CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Poster (3 $^{rd}$ Place)		CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Paper Award	Autonomous Infrastructure,	Management and Security Conference
2015	Top Papers Nomination Brazilian Symposium on Computer Networks and Distributed Systems		
2010	Student Award (3 $^{rd}$ Place)	Computer En	gineer, Federal University of Pará, Brazil

## **Communication Skills**

More than 30 presentations in the last 3 years (see in: http://www.slideshare.net/jjcsantanna), among those I highlight:

2015	<b>Oral Presentation</b>	at Logius (part of the Dutch Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations).
2015	<b>Oral Presentation</b>	to the Dutch National Management Organization of Internet Providers (NBIP).
2015	<b>Oral Presentation</b>	to the Dutch National Cyber Security Centrum (NCSC).
2013 & 2015	<b>Oral Presentation</b>	at the $31^{th}$ and $36^{th}$ IRTF Network Management Research Group (NMRG).

## **Sci**entific Appendix

Description of Ph.D. Research Publications